so
okay hello everyone thanks for joining
this second meeting of the second cohort
of the active inference textbook group
where we're going to be discussing
chapter one
today is september 9th 2022
so i'll minimize this and you guys can
click on my screen and that will show
you the full screen of what i am
presenting
so what we'll do in the live meetings
here for the next two and a half months
or so is totally going to be driven by
the material that's in the chapters
and in the appendices
so we're going to go to the questions
page and we're going to look at the
questions that have been asked for that
week for that theme and we're just going
to start with the most upvoted questions
so here you can upload a question like
this by
clicking thumbs up
um so we will start with the most
upvoted questions and then we can take
notes here and the discourse in this
answers in this course and if you just
click on that it opens this page and
anybody is free to write here
and after addressing the questions which
is probably going to be most of the time
and discussing them
then
we will
move on to maybe look at the ideas more
broadly
over here
so we don't really have too many
questions if anybody wants to jump in
and
write a question
we did send an email reminder that um
because this was pretty empty
over the course of the week but
hopefully thinking by writing in this
way will be a structure where we'll be
able to hear everyone's perspective and
leave the coda in a better place than we
found it so if anybody wants to jump in
and write additional questions in the
coda now would be a good time
and then after looking at the questions
we will pull back and focus a little bit
more broadly so maybe we'll go over here
to touch on the ideas and insights of
the chapter
and then ideas for that week and then in
the last minutes we can just see if
there's been any
changes to the project ideas and start
to see what people are excited about
applying active inference to
um
and then we will end at the top of the
hour
so let's just head over to the questions
the cohort 2 questions page and take a
couple minutes to put some questions in
here
um so just so you guys know control plus
and control minus are good ways to
scroll in and out to get like the right
view of the screen
and then you can hide this little
textbook bar over here so i'm going to
hide that and just give everybody maybe
like five minutes to
put in a question or something they
would maybe like to discuss from chapter
one of
the textbook
so
[Music]
foreign
so
[Music]
so maybe we could just take like one
more minute and wrap up these questions
[Music]
and just want to say like to everyone at
any point that there's always the
affordance of just listening and also of
just
re-watching this recording
there's also the affordance in gather to
raise your hand
um see if i can show where that is
um boy it's been a long time
over here there it is down at the bottom
so there's this raised hand feature
and lower hand
um
yeah okay
let's see
um
and then
if you would you can raise your hand if
you would like to share just on that um
particular question and we're going to
have them up in the coda
and you can also pull up the answers um
in the discourse and that will pull up
the focused view of the question
and everybody um is free to
collaboratively like edit the answers
here in the discourse
it's better to really add and be noisy
even if it's just like a bullet point
list or an incomplete thought or if
there's incoherence or if it's
contradictory those are all fine it just
adds information and perspective on the
question
um so yeah we're going to open up each
question the answers in the discourse
and read what has been read and already
contributed in the answers and then also
people want to share other thoughts that
they're having that's awesome and then
if anybody also just wants to be taking
notes just things that are coming to
mind or they don't want to share in a
speaking way or just taking some notes
on what other people are saying
so this is really a participatory uh
group and
so we it's just is what we make it here
um
okay cool i actually this little window
opener i won't see any raised hands and
gather
all right let's see
i need a double screen
all right let's see if i can do it in
this small way
okay
cool
um all right so let's get into it this
first question i'll pop it open
and it says
what is the difference between a
stimulus response mapping and a state
action policy
um
so i don't know does anybody have any
ideas here i'm not i think that they're
both um kind of like an if this then
that
but
they're specific i think to machine
learning so if anybody has um any of
like more depth or background
in this area that would be awesome to
hear
so i don't know the way i kind of think
about it oh is that uh arun did you
raise your hand
yeah
can you hear me yeah cool
i can give a very i can give an attempt
at an answer to that
um
which
from my understanding and please tell me
if i'm wrong um when you've got the
stimulus response mapping
you've you're con you've got 100
certainty on what the stimulus is
so with the states you're then factoring
in beliefs about
you've got uncertainty so maybe you just
you know at a simple form you could be
chucking a gaussian distribution on
every stimulus and then a gaussian
distribution on
what your response is
to go from state to go from stimulus
response mapping to state action policy
that's my intuitive understanding of
what's going on but again please tell me
if i'm barking on
the wrong track
yeah that's awesome thanks for um
sharing and i kind of think about it in
the same way like i i don't know i mean
this is probably totally wrong but like
i think like about the roomba
like the little vacuum that cleans your
house um and so like if you turn it on
it turns on and moves like that's a
stimulus like you push the button and
then it turns on and then um like it
moves around because you pushed the
power button like it's a very clear
thing versus like the state action like
if it's it's full
like if the vacuum gets full then it
like dumps out but like that state of
fullness is like a right like a
distribution right like so it can be
like more or less full and it senses how
far it is away from the dump out bucket
or whatever so that's like the state
action like the state can be full but
like what like what is too full for the
roomba like is it a certain weight
that's in there or like a certain volume
or sensor i don't know
i have i have uncertainty about when the
room dumps itself out
cool awesome
so we can just write this in here so um
and anyone's free to take notes and type
in here
okay cool all right
so um yeah and anyone's free to just get
in here and
jump in and and do this
all right so
let's look
uh
let's look at this one
all right so this question says
is the brain trying to maximize qualia
divergence and minimize encoding length
ali
sorry i raised my hand before um i was
just wanted to add some comments about
the previous question uh because i think
it's a very important one um you see uh
as we go on uh
specifically specifically in the chapter
four when we encounter the concept of
markup blanket uh will i think
we can see uh kind of more uh granular
differences between those two concepts
between uh stimulus stimulus response
mapping and
state action policy but briefly states
are just representations of um
internal or external world
right and actions are
specifically uh goal-directed called
goal-oriented responses and
they
just try to
change the state
of the system or the agent but when
we're talking about uh just uh stimulus
response mapping i mean response uh
doesn't necessarily tries to change the
state of the agent uh as a as an example
uh if you touch a
hot object
the pain you feel is just a response
right but if you move away your hand
from that hot object it's an action
which tries to change
the stimulus and one other important
distinction here is
the term policy
is used in a different sense in active
inference literature as compared to
reinforcement learning literature
namely
in reinforcement learning this term
is often used to refer to
singular mappings or one-to-one mappings
from states to actions but in active
inference literature policy
usually refers to possible sequence of
actions not just a singular action so
that's i think one important
distinction we need to have in mind also
cool awesome thank you very much and i
looked that up actually
um
so here like i think that um
when they talked about state action
policies they were using it in the
machine learning case because it says
in the textbook the goal directed
character of action and active inference
is in keeping with early cybernetic
formulations but distinct from most
current theories that explain behavior
oh sorry someone's talking could you
please mute
thank you
um
so it says
uh
distinct from most current theories that
explain behavior in terms of stimulus
response mappings or state action
policies so i think that this here um
they're not talking about um the act of
inference state action policies but
they're using it in the reinforcement
learning way so it says also stimulus
response or habitual behavior then comes
a special case of a broader family of
policies in active inference so i think
that the the way that they were talking
about it in the textbook refers to the
reinforcement learning way as opposed to
the active inference way which only is
correct it's definitely um different
any other comments or thoughts on this
question
and thank you for whoever is taking
notes in the coda that's always super
helpful
okay
so we can move on and look at this
question is the brain trying to
maximize qualia divergence and minimize
encoding length
who has some thoughts here
just um
the idea of maximizing qualia divergence
seems like
at some point that's beyond
schizophrenic maybe um so there's like
some maybe
thresholded which
you would not want to go beyond
um
[Music]
and that has seems to have some to me
seems to have something to do with
epistemic value
you can't just maximize try to try to
maximize your epistemic value forever
you would
into a
pragmatic problem
that's encoding length
um
so i'm just i guess i'm wondering if uh
maybe a
a different framing of the question or
commensurate framing of the question is
what's the relationship between
epistemic value and pragmatic value like
are there trade-offs there
yeah i scanned through um chapter one
and really didn't see a
quality of divergence or encoding length
um
there in the chapter
so i'm not really um
yeah
does is this anyone's question do you
want to unpack this question a little
bit more for us maybe
no volunteers
awesome
daniel thanks for joining us i will i
can officially uh
pass the baton off to you and maybe you
have some comments about
maximizing qualia divergence or
minimizing encoding length here but we
got in and we wrote a few questions and
we went through the first one uh we
could also go back and touch on that if
you've got comments on on that as well
that
questions just makes me wonder
what is being minimized what is being
maximized
and when is it
some
particular value that's being minimized
or maximized and when is it the
divergence
between
which other
um differences and in chapter one there
aren't
any of the formalisms yet
but
we'll see a lot of
um
double lines
and kl divergences that will
cue us towards where a divergence is
being at least described
cool
if you're ready i can unshare my screen
and you can
take over but please please continue
okay
um
any more additional additional comments
here
i like this
is oh yeah i thought didn't get to write
this down
but brock had mentioned qualia
divergence
schizophrenia
beyond schizophrenia that was the term
diversity you can imagine is necessary
and some more might be really healthy
and useful
but at some point
i don't
then you're
you have multiple personalities or
something i don't
that makes me think of um
the sense of normalcy
and what is experienced as normal
and how much of a
um
how much of a deviation from normal is
perceived as
like
what what
what is perceived as normal
and where is it perceived as a creative
and maybe even enjoyable
novelty like a guitar solo
and then where is the quality of
divergence too high and maybe
uncomfortable
and then what's the view from the inside
with that actual experience like what
qualia brings in
and then where where is this being
modeled from the outside
with behavioral descriptions
where we we might not be able to
directly address
what the qualia are
and daniel that reminds me like some of
it might be you said some of it might be
normal and some of it might be
uncomfortable and or some of it might be
some divergence might be creative and
some might be uncomfortable and there's
actually like a huge degree of um
of like mental disorder associated with
creativity like i mean studies have been
done and it's like i mean you like i
mean there's the classic like you know
songwriter singer who commits suicide
and we hear this again and again but
there's actually like a great degree of
mapping between the creative type and
some kind of atypical mental state
so maybe both of those are the the same
okay cool anybody have any comments
i don't know if i can see everybody in
my tiny screen go ahead sorry hello hi
it's not clear to me what real what they
precisely means equality diver
divergence because
divergence with respect to what
i mean usually a kl divergence is a
divergence of um like a measure of the
difference between two distribution so
here
what does exactly mean maybe the person
asking the question
and clarify
i'll also just know that they'll go bro
sorry i was just i don't
i don't know if they're here because we
already asked but
to me it just seems like uh internal
kind of
population of one qualia set another
qualia set
that are differentiable like
you can have divergence certainly of
qualia
uh in your own experience if you just
consider you know the various sensory
[Music]
kind of experiential states that you
you occupy like okay so that means that
would mean um
like expanding the range of uh
of your
phenomenology something like that
obviously
yeah so um
yeah so you could imagine a sense of
space and self
you know that's kind of
uh frequent and normative that if that
starts to
um
maybe in a religious or spiritual
setting or
other kind of group team settings it's
you know you kind of get a group flow
going maybe like that that starts to
change
but but maybe
if those two things greatly diverge that
wouldn't be great
so that maybe is related to the
complexity of that part of the model
that encodes
um a representation of the self
so that would increase the complexity of
the
of the model which is one part
one part of
of the free energy minimization scheme
so the
i guess i mean with each increase in the
epistemic
uh import of uh
of the
of
observation then
also complexity of the model though
needs to be kept at bm
within
within some limit
so
inside your blanket so it yeah so it's
probably it's a trade-off between
increasing the complexity of the model
for what concerns
the range of possible experiential
qualia
and their epistemic value i guess
also just mention out of uh fairness
that qualia is not mentioned in the
textbook
but it's totally awesome to consider
what the formalisms entail for
philosophy and many papers and many
discussions do and it's like an
important area to explore
but it's also not what is um
addressed and i i think it's probably
even though these authors in other
settings
tackle the problem
head on
the textbook
is
seemingly crafted
to enable some discussions that might
not
require
the consideration of the view from the
inside or the phenomenology
that qualia entail
and that helps the generality
of the
and the applications across different
systems
and so understanding how they map onto
our
undeniable experience is a great
area to explore
[Music]
no no i was saying that overall the book
doesn't
doesn't expand too much on the on the
part of the model that represents the
the agent itself
as a
you know
as an entity like you know our own
self-representation
that
it it mentions it but does not really
does not really dwell onto it
more about that is probably in the book
of uh jacob hoey
there's a little bit more on that but
in this one not so much
well perhaps this connects to the um
following question
on self-evidencing
so before we jump forward um
i like i just want to stay on this
question for one second so i i looked up
the definition of qualia here um and
it's the the individual instances of
subjective conscious experience and i
don't know maybe
in the question which let's read it
again it says is the brain trying to
maximize qualia divergence and minimize
encoding length
um
so i was wondering if this maybe is
meant for a question like in an
evolutionary sense like is this what the
the brain is trying to do
um across time like in deep time
from you know
prehistory to now
so
um yeah we can move on though because
maybe um self-evidencing is
is uh more addressed in the book than
qualia divergence
um
yeah
so what does self-evidence and
inactivism really mean does anyone want
to take a stab here
yeah i ask the question because um when
i read
up
uh
my eyes just glaze over when i i hit
these words i i can read them in
sentences and i just
just doesn't stick in my
my head what what is really meant
self-evidencing just
it just turns into something
tautological
um
i don't have any sort of
real grasp but what is what is being
said in these sentences
i can take a step at that
because
really it's a it's a it's quite a simple
concept
so if we think about the agent
not as having
a model of the world
but being itself a model of its own
environmental niche
then minimizing free energy basically
means uh
[Music]
working acting
so as to
collect the
the observation
that it expects that is minimizing
surprise
so since
you can say
finding the evidence
for its model of the world
but since the agent is
a model of the world that becomes
self-evidencing
so basically
you could also see it
as trying to find the
sensory
stimulation that is um
that makes your phenotype your organism
viable
that sustains you so that's that's
evidencing me finding the observation
the sensory evidence
that is more coherent
with your
makeup as an organism
thanks
i'll add a few
notes so an activism is a
long-lived thread in cognitive sciences
that is
long existing before active inference
and it is describing
that systems with bodies
real particular things existing in the
world
ought to be
um having their cognition modeled
as bodies engaging with the world rather
than like them taking
like a view from the outside
or um
necessarily needing everything to be
like symbolic communication
whereas in digital systems or kind of
abstractions of cognitive systems it's
very easy to get into some information
and symbol passing
discussions
whereas
for
real systems with biomechanics
and embodiment inactivism brought
attention to the requirement of
considering like the active engagement
of an entity with its niche
so
maybe it's not um a term that provides a
huge cognitive model update because for
many people it's very natural
to consider
cognitive systems as inactive and
embodied
embedded and cultured et cetera et
cetera and sometimes that's called 4e
cognition
and those are all like in allegiance
together but that's what inactive points
towards
and self-evidencing
is describing that the imperative of
systems as modeled under active
inference
is for them to accrue consistent
observations
and find evidence for the kind of thing
that they
expect and prefer themselves to be
and
in the coming weeks we'll explore this
like expect and prefer and how can
expectations be preferences and what
about when we expect bad things to
happen and uncertainty about
expectations but
we can contrast this imperative for
finding consistent
self-consistent or self-evidencing
observations
rather than pursuing rewarding
so one can say i expect and prefer to be
at room temperature
and then moving around the space or
putting the jacket on or off
to reduce surprise
about what observations one is receiving
as opposed to needing to construct a
reward framework
in which room temperature is rewarding
and then it gets less rewarding
and then what is being maximized is the
reward
of the cognitive system
and again in contrast self-evidencing
puts the imperative on
the system's self-model
and reducing surprise about its own
observations
rather than seeing those observations as
just proxy
of reward states that have to be
maximized
aaron
uh i found both of those answers really
interesting and i have a question to
each of those
um
so on the self evidencing
we have so maybe this is fast forwarding
a little bit in the book but they talk
about both generative models and
generative processes and those are
distinct
ideas so when we're talking about
an organism as a model in its niche
it's still distinct from the generative
process right so that's something that
i'm not 100 sure on and i also find the
self-evidencing part a little bit
circular and i don't quite have a good
understanding of that um
so
in my mind the gender model and the
gender process are very distinct and yes
you're looking for
you're an organism and you're in your
niche and you want to succeed and
by natural selection or whatever we only
really see organisms that succeed
um
they're going to look for things that
meet their priors such as you know a
nice
homeostasis food reproduction all of
that sort of stuff that's sort of my
understanding of that part but it's
still an organism using a model to
navigate the world rather than
it is a model itself
um and then also on the idea of the
minimizing free energy but also you know
it's not a reward
to me it sort of is a reward it's just a
reward with respect to a prior
distribution
so
yes you're minimizing free energy and
it's not and
you know you have a prior preference of
being at room temperature that's great
but you're still you still have an
object what an objective function
or functional i think as the book calls
it
you're just subtracting the prior
distribution of temperatures that your
body likes
um
so i still see that as like it's
fundamentally an optimization problem
it's just the units are a bit different
and it's all statistical distributions
and the differences between them rather
than
i don't know
x minus x bar squared
that sort of thing um so those are my
those are the areas i'm not very clear
on um so i don't know if anybody could
clear those up
thank you
thanks
so can i follow up on that then so on
the inactivism
i think the the problem is knowing what
the
the specific meaning of it is compared
with embodied
and embedded because those those e's are
so often used together
what is
where would you say an activism rather
than
embodied and i i think you touched on it
by saying about it involving him having
a model
maybe whereas being embodied
doesn't
i would suggest that inactive
calls the action
into focused whereas the embodiment in
the embedded refer to just the
materiality but the reason why they are
allegianced as 4e eeee etc
they're just fingers pointing at the
moon they're just fingers pointing at
real embodied organisms
and some of the complexities of modeling
them and framing them
in
contrast to disembodied approaches
so
um
they're pointing at organisms
and they're different theoretical
vectors that have been taken
and some of the synthesis amongst them
has already been carried out
yeah the an activism was
[Music]
became popularized the notion with the
francisco varela by francisco varela
actually and
i think
he was not he was not too fond of the
term actually but
anyway
he
the thing is that you wanted to stress
the
the fact that cognition and
consciousness emerges in the circularity
between
sensation and action
so
that was uh it was was enacted in the
circularity continuous circularity
of
action and sensation so
also feel it's
really close to
the free energy approach and active
imprint and so although there are some
of the
early uh
champions of an activism like um
evan thompson and and some other
scholars that
argue that there are actually crucial
differences but
anyway for what concerns the the
[Music]
the difference between the generative
process and the generative model the
generative process is basically
the actual physical processes that turns
causes into
stimuli into
that that impinge on our sensory
surfaces
the generative model is the best gas
that an organism
can make about that so they're not
[Music]
identical of course
the the organism
tries to learn
at its best the
generative process but
you know it's just a model
um
ali
yes and i also wanted to mention um
jacob howie's
well-known paper the self-evidence in
the brain
which i believe is the seminal paper
which introduced this concept of
self-evidencing to active inference
literature
and uh in that paper he also contrasts
this term with inactivism in activists
and all the other
four e-cognition
[Music]
frameworks and theories but uh briefly
he believes that the self-evidencing
brain
by putting a boundary namely the markup
blanket
as
one of its essential components in order
for it to be able to infer
the states of the environment
it can
retain
its cognition within its inner
statistical or generative model
so
that's one of the reason uh the
self-evidencing concept was deemed
necessary to introduce
at the first place
so
and self-evidencing uh is something that
just uh is beyond uh
beyond the biological brain and it it
can refer more generally and more
broadly to
any agent
which
tries to learn about
its environment
as a
as a one dynamical system which tries to
perform inference about
the other dynamical system which is the
outside world
but with a
particular aim of trying towards
the minimizing the error or performing
the allostasis so to speak so
that's one of the main differences
between an activism and self-evidence in
concept here
it's also a very thank you um all for
sharing it's very illustrative to look
at figure 1.2
and see where these terms are used in
the context of the low road and the high
road to active inference
which is one of the key
concepts in this chapter
and it's describing how the following
chapters are going to be structured
so we see self-evidencing on this upper
branch
of the subway system
coming down from the high road
and we see some of these other terms
that people have been mentioning like
generative model
coming up from the low road and then in
the um
in the same page that we were just
discussing
i copied some sections from the text
that are describing these high and low
road
um
they described that the high road
is starting from the question of how
living systems persist and act
adaptively in the world
and so that is very resonant with
self-organization which is the first
stop on that subway system from the high
road
and also um varela's work autopoesis a
lot of questions about how
cognizant sentient systems persist
the high road perspective perspective is
useful to understand
what living organisms must do
and why
why
to be persistent
via surprise minimization not via reward
maximization
and then
what they have to do so it's the what
and the why
in response to the broader question of
how complex systems persist
that's the high road and we've had many
discussions and fun for every person to
also
think about this high road low road
distinction but the high road is
starting from
a
complex system
thriving or persisting
in a complex niche we can think of
and then the low road
is starting from bayes theorem
and continues up through the bayesian
brain
also motivating active inference from a
different direction
and it is describing the low road
perspective is useful to illustrate how
active inference agents minimize their
free energy
well they're not necessarily doing
frequentist statistics
they're doing something that we can
describe as bayesian
and
this textbook is going to introduce
bayes theorem
briefly in a box and it's a
big area and some people will be
familiar
with thinking about priors and updating
priors and the ways that that's
discussed in bayesian statistics
some will be familiar for some it might
be novel
but this is describing kind of the
atomic
computational or statistical
uh nucleus
that is going to describe how
different
systems can fulfill that imperative that
we saw traced out by the high road and
ali i know you'll have a lot to add on
that
uh i've also put a pdf to
carver stream's essay beyond the desert
landscape on
resources and resources page and also on
the chapter one
uh questions and notes page uh
i believe this essay is
the most comprehensively articulated and
in my opinion very beautifully even
poetically articulated
account of the high road and lower
distinctions and the
philosophical distinctions between them
uh if you scroll down i think you can
find the paper i've
attached there
yeah right at the bottom of the page
and i've also inclu appended yeah that's
it the
carl for instance no
[Music]
below that yeah
beyond the
desert landscape uh and i've also
appended uh andy clark's
reply to this essay because uh this
chapter comes from this book called andy
clark and its critics
which uh i think can uh help to
understand
uh the real differences between those
two um concepts and
why it's important
to distinguish between them
when we want to
discuss and understand any
uh
active inference related concepts
thank you awesome thanks i'm gonna just
make note of that in here
maybe
just a comment on the why
if you
[Music]
daniel uh
like talking about the the high road
that
is it is it why really because
my understanding really is uh
the
the perspective
or the nature of the free energy
principle is really a scar says is more
tautological than teleological and why
seems to point to
some sort of teleology so it's
go ahead go ahead
yes
scientific or formal addressments of
teleology or end or goal directedness
are very interesting
and another
framework or
theory which is evolution
has also
threaded the needle
with tautology and teleology
and so there's a lot to be said there um
about how
those two categories aren't necessarily
disjoint
do you believe they have to be disjoint
or are you expecting or preferring that
they are
um if the if the imperative is to
persist and survive
and we simply don't observe systems that
don't
then
that phenomena can be both
taught logical in the sense that it's
self-describing
as well as teleological in that from a
perspective's view
not speaking for the system itself but
from our view on the system
it is acting as if it is trying to
survive
the bubble is acting as if it's trying
to get to the surface of the water
in the sense that it's not acting like
it's trying to go deeper
we don't need to entail any qualia or
any sort of broader theological reason
for that to occur
we can describe something that is both
teleological and tautological
yes well i i think i think i agree
i think that
uh
from what
what car or often says that it's you
know deflationary accounts
is that basically
the
uh
the free energy principle
basically basically describes
a
self-organizing system
uh just because it persists and so
what characteristics
does it need in order to persist
and so in in that sense is uh
topological so
it's just uh you know if it persists in
it must behave like that
so
you don't even need to
put in any imperative to survive if it
survives it must behave like that but of
course as you said you can
frame this
self-organizing drive in a sense as some
sort of imperative to to maintain its
form and function of the organism so
there's a lot of interesting things to
say about that and
uh also
one note is
sometimes we speak in a mode of like
what the imperative is for the system
as itself
in terms of what it normatively should
or imperatively must be doing
but also we can just speak from
ourselves as modelers of other things
as what our modeling imperatives are
and that is a slightly different
question
and that's sometimes known as
instrumentalism which can be compatible
with realism of various flavors and it's
been explored broadly
however
from our perspective as observers things
that are not acting
as to minimize their surprise relative
to some area in space
that makes us say it's that kind of a
thing
if it's not staying in that space which
we're defining as that kind of thing
it's not that thing
if the tornado were not staying in some
range of phase space that we call
tornado
it wouldn't be a tornado to us
and so sometimes that can be a more
empirically grounded
and less speculative stance to have two
feet as us
as modeling systems
which is going to be um consistent with
the meta bayesian approach that's
discussed later in the book
and it
sidesteps or it preempts a lot of very
thorny questions
around speaking for what systems like
actually are or actually are doing
and it's the difference between saying
this the the thing is a model of its
niche
you know big if true
we're going to model it as if it's
a model of its niche
it's irrefutable that's just a choice
that we're taking and someone could say
well i would have taken a different
choice in modeling
and you can say great what would your
choice have been
and there's actually a starting point
instead of just this endless speculation
around what is the system really
and especially when we think about our
markov blankets
and our inability to make direct contact
to hidden states
it it bolsters the the
justification of speaking as a modeler
very cool
um anybody else with comments on this uh
question this self-evidencing and an
activism which we could talk i'm sure
all day about
so if we just finish off that i think
possibly this it's the language that's
the problem with self-evidencing it just
sounds as though it's
self confirmatory
all it's doing is looking for support
bricks existence
which is not a good strategy for
survival
uh why you say that
well if if i only look for evidence of
my existence rather than
uh
things that are a challenge to that
then
it i mean is possibly related to the
dark room
problem yes um exactly yeah
so
in the for the sake of long-term
uh persistence
it may be necessary
to
incur
sometimes transiently
into states that are surprising so
there is no
real
there's no real uh incoherence there i
think
no i i agree
i'm just uh
challenging it it's as a
language
a bit of a language barrier
yeah great great point and indeed the
natural language
is often heavily shading interpretations
and people's conceptions
of different terms like around surprise
belief expectation preference all these
everyday terms
which are core in the act of inference
ontology it's really important to
interrogate our understanding of them
and check their alignment with
formalisms
and um
[Music]
this book
is going to a large extent focus on the
kernel
of the active inference action
perception loop
single agent single level
kernel
and in that way it's very analogous to
like a single linear regression now in
practice
linear aggression on large data sets
does sweeps across families of models
and there's all kinds of things that
come into play just for the linear
aggression
that's the kernel and so
in a nested model one could
reduce
um
surprise and find confirmatory evidence
i'm the kind of thing that seeks out
novel information sources
and
therefore seeking out novel information
sources is confirmatory evidence of that
so once we step into multi-layer models
many of the absolutely valid limitations
of the kernel in and of itself
are addressed
so those are like all the directions
that people's questions on
and written down
are super important
they're all the things that that are
direct adjacencies and relevant for
applications
and there's going to be things about
real complex systems
that the kernel does not describe
totally
so this isn't like
the end of the active inference modeling
of complex systems total book
it really is just describing like the
essence of the loop
so i want to just give aaron the last um
comment because it's the top of the hour
now so
yeah i just wanted to
add to neil's question again like i
fully understand where you're coming
from neil uh when i first read about the
self-evidencing thing i was like that
makes zero sense and exactly what you
described like oh okay you're not gonna
look for predators like as a basic thing
that's not evidence for my existence
that's evidence for my death um but i
think the way i've sort of come around
to it is
it's all about the prior preferences and
what you expect to see
um and
yeah these this
occupation of face space i think is
quite important of you you sort of get
attracted to particular states where
you're comfortable
but you do need to know about the rest
of the world anyway and you have to plan
for not being in those states sometimes
um and so looking for evidence of your
existence
is all about matching those priors and
those priors can be pretty flexible
um so
yeah that's i think that will
in my mind like that comes through a bit
later on in the book i think so
i would say my advice do is stick with
it um but it is it was very
counter-intuitive to me as well when i
first came across it